The following content is provided under a
Creative Commons license. Your support will
help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high quality educational resources for
free. To make a donation or to view
additional materials from hundreds of MIT
courses, visit MIT OpenCourseWare at ocw
.mit .edu. OK. So I'm going to talk about
Gradient Scent today, to get to that
central algorithm of neural nets, deep
learning, machine learning, and
optimization in general. So I'm trying to
minimize a function. And that's the way you
do it. If there are many, many variables,
too many to take second derivatives,
then we settle for first derivatives of the
function. OK. So I introduce, and you've
already met the idea of gradient. But let
me just be sure to make some comments about
the gradient and the Hessian and the role
of convexity before we see the big crucial
example. So I've kind of prepared over here
for this crucial example. The function is
a pure quadratic. Two unknowns, x and y.
Pure quadratic. So every pure quadratic I
can write in terms of a symmetric matrix S.
And in this case, x1 squared was bx2
squared. The matrix is just 2 by 2. It's
diagonal. It's got eigenvalues 1 and b
sitting on the diagonal. I'm thinking of b
as being the smaller one. So the condition
number, which we'll see is all important in
the question of the
speed of convergence,
is the ratio of the largest to the
smallest. In this case, the largest is 1.
The smallest is b. So that's 1 over b. And
when 1 over b is a big number, when b is a
very small number, then that's when
we're in trouble. The condition number of a
matrix, when the matrix is symmetric, that
condition number is lambda max over lambda
min. If I had an unsymmetric matrix, I
would probably use sigma max over sigma
min, of course. But here, matrices are
symmetric. OK. We're going to see something
neat, is that we can actually take the
steps of steepest descent, write down what
each step gives us, and see how quickly
they converge to the answer. And what is
the answer? So I haven't put in any linear
term here. So I just have a bowl sitting on
the origin. So of course, the minimum point
is x equals 0, y equals 0. So the minimum
point x star is 0, 0, of course. So the
question will be, how quickly do we get to
that one? And you'll see a pretty small
example, not typical. But the terrific
thing is that we see everything for this
example. We can see the actual steps of
steepest descent. We can see how quickly
they converge to the x star, the answer,
the place where this thing is a minimum.
And we can begin to think what to do if
it's too slow. So I'll come back. I'll
come to that example after some general
thoughts about gradients, Hessians. So what
does the gradient tell us? So let me just
take an example of the gradient.
Let me take a linear function.
f of x, y equals, say, 2x plus 5y.
I just think we ought to
get totally familiar with these.
We're doing something. You know, we're
jumping into an important topic. When I ask
you, what's the gradient, that's a freshman
question. But let's just be sure we know
how to interpret the gradient, how to
compute it, what it means, how to see it
geometrically. So what's the gradient
of that function? It's a function of two
variables. So the gradient is a vector
with two components. And they are the
derivative with respect to x, which is 2,
and the derivative with respect to y, which
is 5. So in this case,
the gradient is constant.
Which I often call h after Hessian. Or del
squared f would tell us we're taking second
derivatives. That will be the second
derivatives, obviously 0 in this case. So
what shape is h here? It's 2 by 2, right?
Everybody recognizes it. 2 by 2. This h
would have the, I take the second
derivative of that. Oh, sorry. The first
derivative of that with respect to x,
obviously 0. The first derivative with
respect to y. The first derivative of that
with respect to x, y. Anyway. Hessian 0 for
sure. OK. So let me draw the surface. So
x, y, and the surface. If I graph f in this
direction, then obviously I have a plane.
And I'm at a typical point on the plane,
let's say. Yeah. Yeah. So I'm at a point x,
y, I should say. I'm at a point x, y. And
let me put the plane through it. OK.
So how do I interpret the gradient at that
particular point x, y?
What does 2x plus 5y tell me? Or rather,
what does grad f tell me about movement at
that point x, y? Of course, the gradient is
constant. So it really didn't matter what
point I'm moving from. But I'm taking a
point here. So what's the deal? If I move,
what's the fastest way to go up the
surface? If I took the plane that went
through that point x, y, what's the fastest
way to climb the plane? What direction
goes up fastest? The gradient direction,
right? The gradient direction is the way
up. How am I going to put that in this
picture? I guess I'm thinking of this plane
as, so what plane, you could well ask, what
plane have I drawn? Suppose I've drawn the
plane 2x plus 5y equals 0 even.
So I'll make it go through the area.
OK. And I've taken a typical point on that
plane. OK. So if I decrease that function,
I go perpendicular to the plane, right? If
I want to stay level with the function,
if I want it to stay at 0, I stay in the
plane. So there are two key directions.
Everybody knows this. I'm just repeating.
This is the direction of the gradient of f
out of the plane, steepest upwards. This is
the downwards direction minus gradient of
f, perpendicular to the plane, upwards. And
this is, that line is in the plane. That's
part of a level set. 2x plus 5y equals 0
would be a level set. OK. That's my
pretty amateur picture. Just all I want to
remember is these words.
Level and steepest up or down.
Down with the minus sign that we see
in steepest descent. So we're in steepest
descent. OK.
And what's the Hessian
telling me about the surface?
If I take the matrix of second derivatives,
so I have this surface. So I have a
surface, f equal constant.
That's the sort of level surface. So if I
stay in that surface, the gradient of f is
0. Gradient of f
is 0 on the surface.
The gradient of f points perpendicular.
But what about the Hessian? The second
derivative? What is
that telling me about
that surface in particular, when the
Hessian is 0, or other surfaces? What does
the Hessian tell me about? I'm thinking of
the Hessian at a particular point. So I'm
getting 0 for the Hessian
because the surface is flat.
If the surface
was convex upwards from, if it was a
convex graph of f, the Hessian would be?
So I just want to make that connection now.
What's the connection between the Hessian
and convexity of the function? The Hessian
of the function and convexity of the
function. So the point is that convexity,
the Hessian tells me whether or not the
surface is convex. And what is the test?
Positive definiteness. GILBERT STRANGER -
Positive definiteness or semi
-definiteness. I'm just looking for an
excuse to write down convexity.
Strong or strict. Do I say strict or
strong convexity? I've forgotten. Strict, I
think. Strictly convex.
OK. So convexity, the Hessian is positive
semi -definite or which includes, which I
better say that right here,
includes positive definite.
And if I'm looking for a strict convexity,
then I must require positive definite. H is
positive definite.
Semi -definite won't do. So semi -definite
for convex. So in fact, the linear function
is convex, but not strictly convex.
Strictly means it really bends upwards. H
is positive definite. The curvatures
are positive. So this would include linear
functions. And that would not include
linear functions. They're not strictly
convex. OK. Good, good, good. Some
examples. OK. The number one example, of
course, is the one we're talking
about over here. So examples.
X equal 1 half x transpose Sx.
And of course, I could have linear terms
minus A transpose x, a linear term, and I
could have a constant term. OK.
So this function is strictly convex when
S is positive definite. H is now S for that
function. For that function, H. Usually
H, the Hessian, is varying from point to
point. The nice thing about the pure
quadratic is it's constant. It's the same S
at all points. OK. Let me just ask
you, so that's a convex function.
And what's its minimum?
What's the gradient, first of
all? What's the gradient of that?
I'm asking really for differentiating,
thinking in vector, doing all n derivatives
at once here. I'm asking for the whole
vector of first derivatives. And because
here, I'm giving you the whole function
with x for a vector x. Of course, we could
take n to be 1. And then we would see that
if n was 1, this would just be Sx squared,
half Sx squared. And the derivative of a
half Sx squared, let me just put that over
here so we're sure to get it right, half of
Sx squared. This is in the n equal 1 case.
And the derivative is obviously
Sx. And that's what it is here, Sx.
It really just,
you know, it's obviously simple. But if
you haven't thought about that line, it's
asking for all the first derivatives of
that quadratic function. Oh, it's not. What
do I have to include now here? That's not
right as it stands for the function that's
written above it. What's the right
gradient? Minus a. Minus a, thanks.
Because it's a linear function. It's
partial derivatives. They're obviously just
the components of a. OK. And the Hessian
H is S, the derivatives of that guy. OK.
Good, good, good, good. And the minimum
value, we might as well, oh, yeah. What's
the right words for
a minimum value?
No, I'm sorry. The right word is minimum
value, like f min. So I want to compute f
min. Well, first, I have to figure
out where is that minimum reached?
And what's the answer to that? So we're
putting everything on the board for this
simple case. The minimum of f of f
of f of x, remember, it's x's. We're in n
dimensions. Is at x equal what?
Well, the minimum is
where the gradient is 0.
So what's the minimizing x?
S inverse a. Thanks.
And what's the?
Sorry. That's not right.
It's here that I
meant to write it.
Really, my whole point for this little
moment is to be sure that we keep straight
what I mean by the place where the minimum
is reached and the minimum value. Those are
two different things. OK. So the minimum
is reached at S inverse a, because that's
obviously where the gradient is 0. It's
the solution to Sx equal a. And what I was
going to ask you is, what's the right word?
Well, sort of word, made up word for this
point x star where the minimum is reached?
So it's not the minimum value. It's the
point where it's reached. And that's
called, the notation for that point is?
Argmin. Argin. Thanks.
Argmin of my function. And that means
the place, the point where f equals fmin.
I haven't said yet what the minimum value
is. This tells us the point. And that's
usually what we're interested in. We're,
to tell the truth, not that interested in a
typical example of what the minimum value
is as much as, where is it? Where do we
reach that thing? And of
course, so this is xmin. This is then
argmin of my function, f.
That's the point. And it happens to be, in
this case, the minimum value is actually 0.
So it goes,
because there's no linear term, a transpose
x. I guess I feel, why am I talking about
argmin when you've all seen it? I guess I
think that somebody could just be reading
this stuff, for example, learning about
neural nets, and run into this expression
argmin and think, what's that? So it's
maybe a right time to say what it is. It's
the point where the minimum is reached. And
that's, it's the, why those words, by the
way? Well, arg isn't
much of a word.
Strangled. But it's sort of short. I assume
it's short. Nobody ever told me this. I
assume it's short for argument. The word
argument is a kind of long word for the
value of x. If I have a function f of x, f
I call a function, and x is the argument of
the function. You might often, more often,
see the word variable. But argument, and
I'm assuming that's what that refers
to. It's the argument that minimizes the
function. OK, good. And here it is, s
inverse a. Now, but just by the way, what
is f min? Do you know the minimum of a
quadratic? I mean, this is the fundamental
minimization question,
to minimize a quadratic.
Electrical engineering, the quadratic
regulator problem is the simplest problem
there. There could be constraints. And
we'll see it with constraints included. But
right now, no constraints at all. We're
just looking at the function f of x. And
we, let me remove the b, because that just
shifts the function by b. If I erase that,
that's just to say it didn't matter. It's
really that function. So that function
actually goes through 0, right? As it is,
when x is 0, we obviously get 0. But it's
still on its way down, so to speak. It's
on its way down to this point, s inverse a.
That's where it bottoms out. And when it
bottoms out, what do you get for f? One
thing I know, it's going to be negative,
because it passed through 0, and it was on
its way below 0. So let's just figure out
what that f min is. So I have a half. I'm
just going to plug in s inverse a, the
bottom point, into the function and see
where the surface bottoms out and at what
level it bottoms out. So I have a half. So
that's s inverse a is a transpose s
inverse. s is symmetric, so I'll just write
s inverse transpose. s, s inverse a from
the quadratic term minus a transpose. And x
is s inverse a. Have you done this
calculation? It just doesn't hurt to repeat
it.
Write in s inverse a. There, there, and
there. OK, what have I got? Well, s inverse
cancels s. So I have a half of a transpose
s inverse a minus 1 of a transpose inverse
a. So I get, finally, negative 1 half.
Half of it minus 1 of it of a transpose s
inverse a. Sorry, that's not. Brilliant
use of the blackboard to squeeze that in
there, but that's easily repeatable. OK,
good. So that's what a quadratic bowl, a
perfect quadratic problem minimizes to
where that's its lowest level. OK, I wanted
to mention one other function, because I'm
going to speak mostly about quadratic but,
obviously, the whole point is that it's
the convexity that's really making things
work. So here, let me
just put here a remarkable
convex function.
And the notes tell
what is the gradient of this function. They
don't actually go as far as the Hessian.
Proving this is a convex. Proving that this
function I'm going to write down is convex
takes a little thinking, but it's a
fantastic function. You would never sort of
imagine it if you didn't see it there
sometime. So it's going to be a function of
a matrix. It's a function of,
those are n squared variables,
xij.
So it's a function of many variables.
And here is this function. You take the
determinant of the matrix. That's clearly
a function of all the n squared variables.
Then you take the log of the determinant
and put in a minus. And you put in a minus
sign, because we want convex. That turns
out to be a convex function. And even to
just check that for 2 by 2. Well, for 2 by
2, you have four variables, because it's a
2 by 2 matrix. We could maybe check it for
a symmetric matrix and move down to three
variables. But I'd be glad anybody who's
ambitious to see why that log determinant
is a remarkable function. And let me see.
I think it has, so the gradient of that
thing is also amazing. The gradient of
that function, I'm going to peek so I don't
write the wrong fact here.
Yeah. So the partial derivatives of that
function are the entries of, these are the
entries of a inverse.
That's the, of x inverse.
That's like, wow. Where did that come from?
OK. And it might be minus the entries, of
course, because, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So we've
got n squared function. So think of the,
what is a typical entry in x
inverse? What is a typical x inverse ij?
Just to remember that bit of pretty old
-fashioned linear algebra. The entries of
the inverse matrix, I'm sure to divide by
what? Determinant. The determinant. That's
the one thing we know.
And that's the reason we take the log.
Because when you take derivatives of a log,
that will put determinant of x in the
denominator. And then the numerator will be
the derivatives of the determinant of
x. Oh, can we get any idea what are the
derivatives of the determinant? Oh, my god.
How did I ever get into this? So are you
with me so far? This is going to be
derivatives of determinant with respect to
all these variables divided by the
determinant. Because that's what the log
achieved, right? So when I take the
derivative of the log of something, the
chain rule says take the derivative of
that something, divide by determinant of x,
divide by the function determinant
of x. OK. So what's the derivative of the
determinant of a matrix with respect to its
1, 1 entry? Yeah, sure. This is crazy to
be doing this, but it's healthy. OK. So I
have a matrix x. Da, da, da. x, x, 1, 1. x,
1, n.
1, x, n, n. OK. And what am I looking
for? I'm looking for the derivatives of the
detr. Do I want the derivatives of the
determinant? Yes. So what's the derivative
of x of the determinant
with respect to the
first equals what?
How could I figure out? If I change, so
what's this asking me to do? It's asking me
to change x, 1, 1 by delta x and see what's
the change in the determinant, right?
That's what derivatives are. Change x, 1, 1
a little bit. How much did the determinant
change?
I, what has the determinant of the
whole matrix got to do with x, 1, 1?
You remember that there's a formula
for determinants. So I need that fact. The
determinant of x is x, 1, 1 times
something. And it's that something that I
really want to know, plus x, 1, 2 times
other something, plus, say, along the first
row, times another something.
What are these
factors that multiply the x's to give
the determinant? What, that gives a linear
combination of the first row times certain
factors gives the determinant. And how do I
know that there will be such factors?
Because the fundamental property of the
determinant is that it's linear in row
1. If I don't mess with other rows, it's a
linear function of row 1. So it has the
form x, 1, 1 times something. And what is
that something? Determinant of the same
length. The determinant of this. So what
does x, 1, 1 multiply when you compute
determinants? x, 1, 1 will not multiply any
other guys in its row, because you're never
multiplying two x's in the same row or the
same column. What x, 1, 1 is multiplying
are all these guys. In fact, it turns out
to be it's the determinant. And what is
this called? That one smaller determinant
that I get by throwing away the first row
and first column. It's called a? 1, 1, 1.
Minor is good. Yes. Minor is good. There
are two words that can be used. Minor and
cofactor.
Yeah. And what is it? I mean, how do I
compute it? What is the number? This is a
number. And it's this number. But maybe
I think of the minor as this determinant.
Cancel that. Maybe I think of the minor
as this smaller matrix. And the cofactor,
which is the
determinant of the minor.
And there's a plus or minus. Everything
about determinants, there's a plus or minus
choice to be made. And we're not
going to worry about that. But so anyway,
so it's the cofactor. Let
me sort of call it C, 1, 1.
And so that's the formula for the
determinant. That's the cofactor expansion
of a determinant.
OK. And that will connect back to
this amazing fact that the gradient is the
entries of x inverse. And the inverse is
the ratio of cofactor to determinant. So x
inverse, 1, 1, is that cofactor
over the determinant.
Yeah. So that's where this all comes from.
Anyway, I'm just mentioning that as a very
interesting example of convex function.
OK. I'll leave that. That's just for like
education. OK. Now I'm ready to go to work
on gradient descent. So actually, the rest
of this class and Friday's class about
gradient descent are very fundamental parts
of this, of 18 .065. And that will be one
of our examples. And then the general case
here. OK. So I'm using this. I'm not going
to. It would be interesting to minimize
that thing. But we're not going there.
Let's hide it so we don't see it again. And
I'll work with that example.
So here is gradient descent.
OK. So we can
take it as constant.
If we take too big a learning rate, the
thing will oscillate all over the place.
And it's a disaster. If we take too small a
learning rate, too small steps, what's the
matter with that? Takes too long. Takes
too long. So the problem is to get it just
right.
And one way that you could say get it right
would be to think of optimize. Choose the
optimal SK. Of course, that takes longer
than just deciding an SK in advance, which
is what people do. So I think what people
do is, on really big problems, is take an
SK, estimate a suitable SK, and then go
with it for a while, and then look back to
see, was it, if it was too big, they'll
see oscillations in the, you know, it'll be
bouncing all over the place.
Or, of course, an
exact line search.
So you see that this expression
often, an exact line search.
Choose SK to make
my function f at xk plus 1 a minimum on the
line, on the search line, in the search, a
minimum in the search direction.
The search direction is given by
the gradient. That's the direction we're
moving. This is the distance we're moving,
or a measure of the distance we're moving.
And an exact search would be to go along
there. If I have a convex function, then as
I move along this line, as I increase SK,
I'll see the function start down, because
the gradient negative gradient means down.
But at some point, it'll turn up again. And
an exact line search would find that point
and stop there. OK. That doesn't mean we
would, you know, we will see in this
example where we will do exact line
searches that
for a small value of b, it's extremely
slow. That the condition number controls
the speed. That's really what my message
will be just in these last minutes and next
time, the sort of key lecture on gradient
descent. OK. So an exact line search would
be that. So what a
backtracking line search.
Backtracking would be take a fixed s. Like
1. And then be prepared to come backwards.
Cut back by half. See what you get at
that point. Cut back by half of that to a
quarter of the original step. See what that
is. And when you, if you're, so the full
step might have taken you back to the
upward sweep. Halfway forward might still
be on the upward sweep. Might be too
much. So backtracking cuts the step size in
pieces and checks until it,
so s0, half of s0, quarter of s0, or
obviously a different parameter, a s0, a
squared s0, and
so on until you're
satisfied with that step. And there are,
of course, many, many refinements. We're
talking about a big algorithm here that
everybody finds has, depending on their
function, has different experiences with.
OK. OK. So here's my fundamental question.
What, if I do, let's think of an exact.
Like how much does that reduce the
function? How much does that reduce the
function? So that's really what the bounds
that I want are. How much does that reduce
the function? And it will, we'll see that
the reduction involves
the condition number, m over m.
So why don't I turn to the example first,
and then where we know exact answers. That
gives us a basis for comparison. And then
the math goal is prove, get bounds on the
size of f that match. So we can match what
we see exactly in that example, where we
know everything. We know the gradient. We
know the Hessian. It's that matrix. We know
the condition number. So what
happens if I start at a point x0, y0?
That's on my surface.
Sorry. What do I want to do here?
That, yeah. I take a point, x0, y0.
And I iterate.
OK. So here's the new x, y, k
plus 1 is x, y, k minus the s, times,
which I can compute, times the gradient
of f. So I'm going to put in gradient of f.
What is the gradient here?
The gradient, the derivative is with
respect to x. So I have a 2x, k, and 2by,
k. Right? That's my, and
this is the step size. OK.
And for this small problem, where we're
going to get such a revealing answer, I'm
going to choose exact line search. I'm
going to choose the best x, k. OK. And
what's the answer? So let me, I just want
to tell you what the iterations are for
that particular function, starting at
x0, y0. Start. So let me put start x0,
y0.
And I'll tell you about that in a month,
in two or three weeks. And I'll tell you
about that. So OK. So here are the x, k's
and the y, k's and the f and the function
values. OK. So x, k.
So where am I going to start?
Yeah. So I'm starting from the point x0, y0
equal b, 1. Turns out that'll make it. Our
formula is very convenient. x0, y0 equals
b, 1. Good. So OK. So x, k is b times the
key ratio, b minus 1 over b plus 1 to
the k -th power. And y, k happens to be 1.
Ratio. And my function
f has the same ratio, too.
This is f, k. Has that same ratio, 1 minus
b over 1 plus b to the k -th times f, 0.
That's my, that's the beautiful
formula that we're going to.
Take as the best example possible. Let's
just see. At k equals 0, I have x, k equal
b, y, k equal 1, b starting at b, 1. And
that tells me the rate of decrease of the
function. It's the same ratio. So what am I
learning from this example? What's jumping
out is that this ratio, 1 minus b over 1
plus b is crucial. That that's the, if b is
near 1, that ratio is small. If b is near
1, that's near 0 over 2. And I converge
quickly. No problem at all. But if b is
near 0, if my condition number is bad, so
the bad case, the
hard case, is small b.
So I'm going to change that picture to a
picture in the xy plane of the level sets.
Yeah. So the picture really to see is
in the xy plane. The level sets f equal
constant. That's what a level set is. It's
a set of points x and y where f has the
same value. And what
do those look like?
Let's see.
What do you think? What do you think?
What do the level sets look like for this
particular function? If I look at the curve
x squared plus b y squared equal constant,
that's what a level set is. This is x
squared plus b y squared equal a constant.
What kind of a curve is that?
That's an ellipse. And what's up with that
ellipse? What's the shape of it? So it's
because there's no xy term, that ellipse
is well lined up with the axes. The major
axes of the ellipse are in the x and y
directions because there is no cross term
here. And we could always have diagonalized
our matrix if it wasn't diagonal. And that
wouldn't have changed anything. So this
is just rotating the space. And we've done
that. OK. So what do the level sets look
like? They're ellipses. And suppose b is a
small number. Then what's with the
ellipses? If b is small, I have to take a
pretty large y to match a change in x. I
think maybe they're ellipses of that sort.
Are they?
It comes down steeply in the y direction.
But in the x direction, I'm crossing the
valley slow. Is that right? So what happens
if I take a point there? Oh, yeah. Ah, I
remember what to do. So let's start at that
point on that ellipse. OK. And those were
the level sets, f
equal constant.
Search direction. What
direction do I move from x0, y0?
Do I move along the ellipse? Absolutely
not, because along the ellipse, f is
constant. The gradient direction is
perpendicular to the ellipse. So I move
perpendicular to the
ellipse. And when do I stop?
Pretty soon. Because very soon, I'm going
back up again. So I start some, well, I
don't know whether you will.
Yeah. I haven't practiced with this curve,
but I know. And time's up, thank God. But
what do I know is going to happen? And by
Friday, we'll make it happen. So what do we
see for the curve, the track of the,
say it? Zigzag. It's a zigzag. Yeah. So we
would like to get here, but we're not aimed
here at all. So we zig, zig, zigzag, and
very slowly approach that point.
And how slowly? With that? With that
multiplier, 1 minus b over 1 plus b. So
that's what I'm learning from this example,
that that's a key number. And then you
could ask, well, what about general
examples? This was one specially chosen
example with the exact solution. Well,
we'll see at the beginning of next time
that for a convex function, this
is typical. It's this 1 minus b is the
critical quantity, or 1 over b, or how
small is b compared to 1. So that will be
the critical quantity. And we see it in
this ratio, 1 minus b over 1 plus b. So if
b is 1 hundredth, this is 0 .99 over 1 .01.
It's virtually 1. OK. So next time is sort
of a key lecture to see what I've just
said, that this controls convergence of
steepest descent, and then to see an
idea that speeds it up. That idea is called
momentum, or heavy ball. So the physical
idea is if you had a heavy ball right there
and wanted to get it down the valley toward
the bottom, you wouldn't go perpendicular
to the level sets. Not at all. You'd let
the momentum of the ball take over and let
it roll down. So the idea of momentum
is to model the possibility of letting that
heavy ball roll instead of directing it by
steepest descent at every point. So there's
an extra term in steepest descent, the
momentum term that accelerates it. OK. So
Friday is the day. See you then.